All our friends in this video, we're going to talk about something which you would definitely
use every single day in your life as a Java developer.
And that's the concept of a Java Bean.
So first things first, what is a Java Bean?
And why did I say we would use it every single day?
Why is it omnipresent in the Java ecosystem?
Whether you're using core Java, you're using any advanced frameworks or something else,
you would most likely be using Java Beans somewhere down the line.
So what is a Java Bean and why do we use it?
So first, the why is that it acts like a data carrier, right?
Or for sending data from one layer to another, you would require something like a Java
Bean.
Obviously in the next video when we would get our hands dirty, put in some code, you would
understand what I'm talking about sending data between layers.
But for now, what is a Java Bean in Java?
So it's a class.
Again, first things first, right?
Let me make it simple for you to understand yet another time, a Java Bean is a class, but
which adheres to a convention, right?
It is an ordinary class like you have written classes, but which adheres to a set of conventions.
And the first one is that a Java Bean has to have instance variables, which are declared
private.
So instance variables in a Java Bean are private.
Let me write that for you.
Obviously, you will know that private is a keyword.
So it starts with a small.
So don't go with what I'm writing here on my whiteboard.
But instance variables have to be declared private.
And by the way, that is one of the industry standards, that's the recommendation, whether
you're using a Java Bean or not, you should always declare instance variables as private.
Right.
Even if you do not, obviously that's not an error, that's why I said you should.
I did not say must when I say must think about that as being an error or not, but when
I say should, it is a recommendation as and as I've been telling you, and following along
in the scores, we are following recommendations as if they're rules.
So that by the end of the scores, you have a tighter hold on the syntax and as I said,
that that goes a long way in your writing quality, better, readable, cool.
So coming back to a Java Bean, whatever variables that you declare, they should be private.
And I was telling you about the recommendation also, why should we declare instance variables
of a class as private?
Because we should never share the state of the program directly, state of a classes instance
variables holds something substantial related to that object.
And we should never share that publicly or without private right.
So that's the first property.
The second property of a Java Bean is that it should have public getter and set of methods.
Right, that is we should, because we now have instance variables as private, how would you
make the outside world to access them by public get a set of methods.
So you should have methods, which are getter and set more on that in the next video.
And we write some actual code, but the getter set of methods should be declared as public
because they would then allow someone else to access these instance variables and third
property of a Java Bean is it should have a no argument constructor.
In short, we call that a no arc constructor.
Right, so it can have as many as parameterized constructor, but at all times, it should have
a no argument constructor, constructor, which does not take any arguments.
And once a class has all these three in it, it is following the convention of a Java
Bean, we refer to that class as a Java Bean, and that is what it really is.
And in the next video, I'm going to go into the implementation details, how do you write
a Java Bean?
And it's especially important, because as I said, something that you use every day,
you definitely would need to have a great understanding of that concept.
So I'll see you in the next video and the code is coming for you shortly.